yes um then you're writing uh yeah oh great thanks
All right, well, we'll get started.
this is week four so we'll recover tonight will be the last new material for the midterm midterm
will be in two weeks so it's at week six so I give you extra like I give you the week to do
your homework and then have questions and all that so we'll do some review next week as well
we'll do some review tonight probably toward the end I'll talk about the plan for tonight in a
I do want to point out I am moving office hours up a little earlier for tomorrow.
Normally they're at 730 to 815, but I've got something in the evening, so I'm going to
move them up a little bit to a little bit earlier.
Nobody's been coming to office hours, so please send me a discord message if you do plan to
come and I will fire up the zoom.
I will be watching, but if nobody's sending me a message, I'm not going to bother.
I've got other work to do, so I'll do it.
So that's tomorrow. I will be traveling Thursday through Sunday, so my
availability may be limited to respond to questions. I will try to get back to
you as soon as I can. I'll be out of town so I will have my phone and I'll be able
to read your messages, but usually when you have messages that are substantive I
have to get to my laptop and look at the specific problem that's involved
with your questions so that I can give you a good answer and if I have a busy
weekend like I had last weekend I can't always get back to questions. So just be aware of that
and I will try. But if I fail to respond to you within 24 hours during the week
please send me a message and I will, I might forget because I'm getting busy with traveling
so just send me a message. I'm not trying to ignore you. I've just got too many things going on.
So that's that.
If you got an email from me today, if you're in section 941, you need to go,
the email was about scheduling the exam.
I do ask that everybody taking the exam in the classroom registers in the
intranet for that.
Now that doesn't apply to you if you are in section 901,
because in Section 901, you are taking the exam here by default.
There is no way for you to schedule through the proctoring system.
So for 941 only, make sure you're registering for the exam if you haven't already.
We do have limited slots in the classroom, so get your registrations in now.
We will also plan on week six to have lecture for the second half.
So we'll be next week and into week six, we'll be diving into new material for the second half of the course.
So be aware of that.
Any questions about any of those housekeeping items?
Okay.
Good.
Plan for today.
We've got some review stuff.
I'm going to go over the quiz as kind of a warm-up and any homework questions you may have.
We're going to go back through and do some examples with map, filter, and fold.
Then what I've decided I'm going to do, I have done this a little bit differently before,
but I think this is going to work better if I do the new slide discussions of the new topics here.
And then whatever time is left, it might be 45 minutes, it might be an hour, it might be more than an hour.
At the end, we'll do some review work going back through the study guide.
I've picked out specific questions to look at in the study guide.
Some of the stuff we're covering tonight that's new is in the study guide,
but we won't do that stuff tonight because you haven't had a chance to go think about it or study it.
So next week we'll spend some time on that as well.
So that's the plan in the next couple weeks.
Any questions about that?
Good.
So let's get started with a quiz.
The first three questions are very similar to one another.
This is about that whole thing we talked about with statements and expressions.
And remember we said that some languages have statements, and some languages have expressions,
and some languages have both.
In fact, most languages that have statements also have expressions.
I can't think of any that don't have both of them except for one.
So, these are three questions that are very similar.
We have C, Java, and Scala.
So do we think that C has statements and expressions both?
Yes.
That's a yes.
You agree?
All right.
That is correct.
How about Java?
True.
Also?
Right.
Cool.
How about Scala?
False.
What do we have in Scala?
Expressions and only expressions.
Right.
Great.
I'm learning Rust right now,
and Rust has both statements and expressions.
So, just as you study languages,
and then you go out in the world and learn new languages,
you can apply these ideas to your learning.
In fact, I'm working through the Rust programming
language book, and I'm finding that I'm going a little,
I'm slow because of my busy life,
but when I tackle chapter,
I get through it a lot faster than,
maybe I would have before I took a class like this.
So this is just a testament to what this kind of material can help you
in terms of thinking about programming languages.
All right, now we've got some Scala code.
So this next question is going to have us run some Scala code in our minds.
We can also, when we're doing a quiz, of course, we can do it in the REPL.
But for this Scala code, we have this function.
It takes two integers, and it produces an integer.
So it looks like it does something like taking the x value and adding it twice,
and then adding the y value to it.
So hopefully this is pretty simple.
What do we think the answer is when we run the function f with the arguments 2 and 3?
We get 7.
You get seven.
Okay, hopefully that was easy.
This is why we do this as a warm-up, right?
Like we're getting ready to deep dive into complicated stuff.
Okay.
All right.
This one always throws me for a little bit of a loop.
So here we have this expression.
I don't know if that's too small.
I gotta get a little better.
This expression has this embedded if expression inside of it.
So, what happens when we run this?
What do we get?
ABE.
Okay, so Dylan thinks it's ABE.
Does somebody have a different opinion?
I wasn't thinking that you did, I just heard two people talk.
So A, B, E.
All right, so let's kind of look through this.
So we have A here, and we have this in parens here.
We have this if 2 plus 3 greater or equal 4, then B, else C plus D.
And I never remember if it's else C, and then this whole thing is adding D on the end or not, right?
So when I was looking at it last night, I think I popped it into the repl.
So we know we're going to begin with an A, and we know we're going to end with an E.
So, looks like all of these, so that doesn't help us at all, right?
So, now we have to sort of reason about what's going on in here.
So, we know now 2 plus 3 is going to be 5, which will be greater than 4.
So, we're going to get a B.
So, we can eliminate the first one.
We can eliminate the third one and the fourth one.
So, we're left with these two, right?
And if we, we don't even need to put it in the REPL
because we know we're going to get B and not C.
B and not C.
So I contend we're going to get 1ABE.
Do you agree?
Yeah.
I'm doing this in my head, and I'm also tired today.
So if I screw up, tell me.
So if it was, say, not greater than, what would we get then?
Would it be a...
Let's find out.
That's a great question, Dylan.
Yeah.
So first, let's test our understanding.
I'm going to just put the thing in here to see what I can sort of add.
See if my brain is fried too much or not.
So, we should get ABE, right, okay cool.
So, Dylan is asking what happens if we make it not greater or
equal to like make this condition fail.
So, what we'll do is we'll say less than,
because we'll just flip the logic, right?
Do we get ACDE?
So it's actually doing, it looks like it's doing this as the full
else lock, if you will.
Right?
It's not really how we usually talk about,
I usually say that because I'm looking at braces and
my languages let's see.
But it's going to do this before,
it's gonna make this whole thing be else.
That's a good question, and that's what throws me in time,
because I don't normally, I would not,
I would probably write that so
that so that the next person who looked at the code
would not have to do that extra work
to figure it out. That's what I think, if I'm ready, but
it's good to know.
Alright, so we're going to say this one's ABE.
Alright,
this next one, we have this node class. Now this is going to be
A little different than our, how we're used to doing lists in Scala.
This one's going to be more like the way we do lists, linked lists in Java, right?
So, they're using null to indicate the end of the list,
just like we would in data structures one when we do linked lists
and we do that with a static class node in Java.
So looks like we have a function that does what?
How would we describe your behavior as function?
In like, one sentence.
I can't understand, go ahead, say it again.
Finding the last variable in the list, return.
Finding the last one.
Last variable in the list.
variable, the last element.
Yeah, and then what?
There's a little more than that.
Subtracted by.
Subtracting by.
Right, so it's basically finding the last element in the list and
subtracting one from its value and that's the value it returns.
Okay, so if we, the question is above, right?
I scrolled too far.
So, we're passing it with this list of 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 in that order.
So, what do we get back?
Using that description should be 11, so the way we got that is,
we're basically just going to keep going to the next element in the list.
As we take the list apart, we're going to process the list,
we're not really taking it apart,
we're sort of looking at it from a different element, right?
I usually use the way is the expression like when I speak about it like deconstructing
what's we're not really we're sort of deconstructing but we're not using the
pattern matching stuff that we would be in scottlobless so anyway we're walking
through the list we get to the end the last element is 12 so 12 minus 1 is 11
Okay, so now I'm gonna make this a little, or this probably, yeah, okay.
So which of the following is the correct definition of a function to multiply all of the numbers
in a list?
So what do we think?
Well I should probably move the mouse so we can read all that.
Is that too small?
There's so many answers that I wanted to them.
I could zoom it in and we can just decide if it's the first three,
and then move on.
So is it one of the first three?
First one.
Say again?
So, okay.
Okay, that one looks like it could be. Let's come back to that. Let's look at the next one.
So what about this one? So if it's empty, we have one.
Otherwise, we're going to do this. Does this work?
No, that doesn't work.
Why not?
Because 1 doesn't have a tail.
Because more generally, int doesn't have a tail.
So we're calling product recursively,
we're getting back an int, we can't call tail.
So int compiler says, nope, you can't do that.
So it's not 2.
So for 3, would that compile?
Would the third one compile?
I'm hearing some no's.
Okay. Tell me why.
A couple of reasons.
Well it's going to hit the first reason and not compile, but.
So what do we see here?
it do first when this executes? What is it trying to if it were to execute what
would it try to do?
Trying to multiply excess head with the tail. Yes, does that make sense? So you have a head
which is an int, right, and then you have a tail which is a list of ints. Does it
makes sense to multiply those. No, so that'll fail. The other thing is, well I
don't know whatever the result of that would be, this is not the reason why the
compilation fails, the compilation won't fail. But if you were to do something
that was valid for multiplication, like let's say excess dot head times three,
would that compile at that point? Like I'm saying I'm just replacing this excess
that tail with a 3. I'm making that up as I go. Would that compile? Also no, but why would that not compile?
It takes a list of ints? Because the product function takes a list of ints and if we're trying to pass a single int,
that's not going to compile. So for a bunch of reasons, this one is, well for the first reason, but I just wanted to use that.
use that as to illustrate. Fourth one, let's see. So this one, again, what happens first
when we execute this? What happens? What do we try to do if we were to execute it? Maybe
Maybe it does compile, I don't know, you tell me.
First thing that happens is what?
This.
So, can we take a head and multiply by the rest of the list?
Or by the whole list?
Not the rest, but the whole list.
So it's the same kind of problem, right?
The type doesn't line up, right?
So you can't do this, so right?
At least here you're trying to do, it looks like you're trying to call tail here.
which would give you a list, but you're not going to have a list here, so.
Okay, now we have this one, so if XS is empty, then 1, otherwise,
we take the head and we multiply by the product of the tail.
Did that work?
I think so, that looks promising.
Someone in the beginning thought number one was going to work, so let's see.
Ah, what's different about this one and the last one?
If statement.
Yes, the contents of the, you know, the then part specifically, right?
So what happens if we have an empty list and we try to call head?
Error.
Yeah.
What kind of error?
No pointer.
No, I think it's a no such element.
You don't have to memorize that.
Is that a compile-time error or a run-time error?
Runtime.
So you said compile time.
Why do you think it's compile time?
Oh, okay.
I thought I heard compile time.
So at compile time, what happens?
Well, this says, okay, if XS is empty, that compiles, then XS, which is a list, you call the head.
It's like a method that's implemented on the list that can compile, right?
We don't really know.
Like, it doesn't, it's not smart enough to, like, even though we can look at this and say, well, it's empty.
So this would, you know, the compiler doesn't reason that.
Like, the compiler just says, does this type have this function?
Yes.
Or method.
Does this type have this method?
Yes.
Compiles.
just fine, but you run it, you will always get a no such element error, or exception,
I think they call it. So the answer can't be one. So I contend the answer is the last one.
And the difference here is, if you think about it, when you get to the empty list and you're
multiplying, if you were to use something else like zero, you would end up doing what?
What would you get for every possible thing you pass to product?
Zero.
0 because you get to the end and you're just multiplying you've got a 0 term in
multiplication you're gonna get a 0 back you're always going to get a 0 back as
you roll up of recursion so that's why it has to be 1 because 1 is the
multiplicative identity mathematically speaking right right next one alright so
I'm going to shrink it just a little to get it all on the screen.
Consider the Scala conditional with expressions e1, e2, and e3 in general form.
So we have this if e1, then e2, else e3, right?
Pretty basic if, then, else.
What is the difference between if and a function like plus on strings or tail on lists?
So what is the difference between if and a function like plus on strings, or a tail on lists?
Why is tail a function and not a method?
It is a method, so I think the wording here is bad.
here is bad. Sorry. I didn't think about it carefully because I imported it from
somebody else but that's a good question. Thank you. So function and or method like
plus on strings or tail on lists. So what's the difference, or is there no difference?
So let's go through the arguments, or the answer choices. So first one is, there is
there is no difference. If is a function defined using this. So, this is asserting that when I have if in my language,
I am actually using some function called if like this. Do we think that could be the answer?
What happens when we have a function that's defined like this?
Tell me about these parameters.
We talked a little bit last week about a topic.
And this was one of the, close to one of the examples.
They will be evaluated.
Okay. You're on to something.
So when I pass an argument into one of these parameters,
and that is actually the correct way to say it.
The argument is what you're passing in,
the parameter is what receives what you're passing in.
Okay? So I have to do what to get an E2?
You said it.
Evaluate it.
I have to evaluate it.
So when I call the function, if this were a function I were calling,
this E2 expression would have to be evaluated always
because of the way this is written.
And this E3 expression would have to be evaluated always
How is that different from this?
E3 won't be evaluated until E1 is false.
E3 is only evaluated.
I'm gonna change your words just slightly, but you were right.
E3 is only gonna be evaluated if E1 is false.
And E2 is only gonna be evaluated if E1 is true.
So, we have this idea of strictness.
So this is an example here. This expression here is non-strict because E2 is not necessarily evaluated unless during execution E1 evaluates the true.
Likewise for E3. E3 is not evaluated unless E1 evaluates the false.
but in a function like this
the way this is written in Scala
we are required to evaluate
both e2 and e3
as well as e1
before the function
can actually execute
and it could be a method actually
so there is actually some web page
out there that I used to link to in the slides
and it's like methods and functions are different
but
for most practical purposes
you can think of them as the same
So going back to the question that someone asked a little while ago, really what it comes down to is that you're a method if you are, a function is a method if it's defined on a class.
Or I guess a method is, it's more proper to say, a method is something defined on a class whereas a function is defined without a class.
It's sort of, you're not defining your own class.
Oh, actually
in Scala that's even more
obscure. So I think the way
the slide's presented is if you see def
you have a method and if you
see val, let's see
if I say def
foo
x
int
string
that's going to be a method
because of this def
and it's going to be defined in whatever class that you are in.
Because remember, it's compiling in Java.
This, if I wanted to do the same thing,
I would have to do val foo, and I would have to say,
and this is, I'm putting the type in.
I have an int, and I'm getting back a string.
So this is a function.
So Scala makes this distinction.
But whenever you see def, it's part of a method and it's part of the class somehow.
So just to clarify that question, that point about that question that was asked earlier.
Okay. So, strictness, non-strictness.
Okay, so what is the difference between if and a function like plus on string?
So what is the method plus on?
Actually, I don't know if Scala defines the plus on a string as a function or
method and it kind of doesn't matter.
But when we do a plus on strings, what are we doing?
We're, what's that?
Concatenating.
And when we concatenate two strings, what do we have to do in order to do that concatenation?
Literally what happens in memory is if you have like foo and bar and you're concatenating,
What's happening is the JVM is allocating, I think it's six slots.
And it's literally copying.
I can't remember if the JVM uses zero termination.
I don't think it does.
It's literally copying each of these.
So in order to do that literal copying, it actually has to evaluate.
It has to know what the strings are.
So if you have some complex expression, like you're calling a function or a method,
and you're getting back a string, you have to do that first and get the string back,
and then do whatever's on the right side of the plus and do that part,
and then that's going to be held in memory,
and then this copying is going to happen to create the new string.
So plus on strings is going to be strict.
Does everybody agree?
Because you have to actually evaluate each side of the what's on the side of the plus.
How about tail on lists?
Does that have to be strict?
Trick question, I guess, maybe.
I don't know.
not really a trick question. So the answer is it has to be, because the way
lists are defined. Everything is sort of constructed in memory, right.
There is something we'll talk about today and in another lecture called a
lazy list where that's not true, but in a regular tale it is. Okay so
now we have to look through the other ones. So this one is not the answer, right.
there is a difference because of the way we're evaluating the arguments.
So this one here, functions take exactly one argument,
but conditionals take three arguments.
Is that true or false?
Functions take exactly one argument, but conditionals take three arguments.
Think carefully.
I love English because that's like, it's a conjunction that's and, right?
So both of those, both parts of that have to be true.
So is it true to say that functions take exactly one argument?
Is that true?
No.
It is true of curried functions, which we talked about last week.
So what this question is, this is the trick question, right?
because what this is doing is it's implying that there is some connection
between curried functions and this statement here.
And without the word curried, it doesn't make it that way.
So that's not true.
Conditionals take three arguments.
Sure, maybe they're not evaluated, but they take three.
But I would say this is false.
So the third one, the conditional in Scala is a statement that functions our expressions.
Hopefully that one's like ding ding ding like something's wrong there. What's wrong with that
one? Scala doesn't have statements. Correct! We just covered that at the
beginning of the quiz, right? Scala doesn't have statements. So this one's not true.
Functions in Scala are statements, but the conditional is an expression. Again,
no statements in Scala so we can move along the next one. The conditional
expression must not evaluate all of its arguments unconditionally but a
a function does evaluate all of its arguments unconditionally.
So this is the best answer.
This is, I would argue that maybe I should fix the wording
a little bit because this function uses something
called call-by-value.
Call-by-value implies that we are evaluating all the arguments.
If we use the little arrow here before the type,
That would be a call by name that would make the parameter
call by name.
And call by name parameters are not strict
when they're declared like that.
We don't have that.
So by default in Scala, we will evaluate
all of the arguments to the function unconditionally.
So I think that is the correct answer.
Number nine. Consider the following Scala program. So we have this function F. What does it do?
In English?
it's always going to return what?
Zero.
It's always going to return zero.
So this is a somewhat contrived function.
Does everybody see why it always returns zero?
It just keeps subtracting.
If it's less than or equal to zero, it's going to return zero.
If it's, so zero is going to give me zero, minus one is going to give me zero.
If it's 3 or 5, I'm gonna just keep recursively calling f until I get down to 0.
I'm always subtracting 1 when I call f, so it's just gonna keep doing that.
So the question asks, and this is really a question about,
how many times do we call the function?
And not so much what does the function produce.
So how many times is F called in total if we have F of 5?
Six times.
I agree with that, you want to explain your logic?
Well-
Why is it not 5?
Well because, you have to count the first time when it goes through when
it puts 5 in- Yep.
Already.
And then you go down, and then eventually you reach 0 but
but by the time you reach zero, it's already out of it.
Yeah, that's pretty good.
I mean, it's not a complicated thing.
So sometimes I'm just trying to teach you how to speak about these things, right?
Because we taught programmers, we talk about this stuff all the time.
The way I like to think about it is we start with we call F and we pass 5 and
then we call it again and we pass 4 and we pass 3 and we pass 2 and we pass 1 and
we pass 0.
and that's the last time we call it,
and then we return, right?
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Count them up, right?
This will become really useful for the next question.
So yes, good job.
Six.
This one, what does this function do?
It also is gonna return zero, always, right?
Do you see that?
Because even if you call this, you're gonna end up.
Oh, actually, if it's minus 1, it might go on forever.
So let's assume that we're always, well, for the sake of this, we're calling f of 4.
So we're okay, because we're not passing something.
It's not going to run forever.
But if we pass f of 4, how many times are we calling it?
Yes, it starts to explode in your head, right?
And I'm too lazy, so this is what I do.
Well, f of 4, I'm going to then call f of 3,
and just hold that thought,
because I'm going to defer the execution
that's actually happening right away.
Later on, I'm going to call f of 3 again.
Now that we've done that,
let's start to see this pattern.
When I call f of 3, I'm going to do f of 2,
f of 2, right?
And then over here, the other f of 3 is going to do f of 2 and f of 2.
And then for each of the 2s, we're going to call f of 1.
And so on, down to 0, right?
We stop at 0.
Yep.
So 0.
You see the pattern, I'm going to just sort of smush them on each other because I'm running
out of room.
You can count them up or you can actually just say well 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 13, 13, 13,
13, 13, 14, 13.
There are eight ones, there are four twos, there are two threes, and there's one four.
So this will be 16 plus 8 plus 4 plus 2 plus 1, so we get 28, 30, 31.
I do this a lot when we do order of growth in data structures.
I draw these things like this because sometimes these recursive functions can sort of explode
in your head, and you're like, you know, you start, you do F of 5.
You've got a whole other tree of 4 over here, right?
And so it starts exploding.
It's exponential.
So in this case, it's going to be 31.
Yeah.
All right.
And those are all of our questions.
So I'm going to go ahead and submit this and make sure that we have .
Can I go back?
We can go back.
But it's too late.
We will go back.
Let me finish the quiz.
I messed something up.
Isn't that what you were going to call me out on?
I just want to mention you that question 3 is a wrong answer.
I did the wrong answer for question 3.
Yeah.
How did I do that?
You didn't stop me.
Did I just click the wrong thing?
Yeah.
That's probably what I did because we talked about this.
That's the statements and expressions stuff, right?
Question 3.
What did I have?
True.
Oh, well, that's wrong.
I know the answer.
It should be false.
I just clicked the wrong one.
Yes.
So you knew that the whole time and you didn't tell me.
I just don't want to interrupt you.
You're very polite.
Thank you.
But you can interrupt me, especially when I mess up.
Got it.
Because I don't want people sitting there seeing that and getting messed up.
I clicked the wrong thing because I was too fast.
Does everybody understand what everyone in the classroom is pointing out?
Is that I had selected the wrong answer for these.
So let's just review them quick.
C uses statements and expressions.
Yes.
Java, statements and expressions.
has only expression. So I said that verbally, but somehow I clicked the wrong one.
Thank you. Feel free to interrupt me if I mess up.
I'm not perfect.
Somebody went out and I read my professors once and wrote like, he messes up in class.
And it's like, well, yeah I do. I am human. I'm not perfect.
Okay, cool.
So, that's our quizzes.
Does anybody have anything from homework 3 that they want to talk about?
Anybody online?
Going once, going twice.
Okay.
Then what we'll do is we will dive into our new material,
And if we have time, we'll spend some time doing a review at the end.
We're gonna start with a little more warm up.
These are examples of map, filter, and fold, which we talked about last week.
I find that kind of coming back and looking at this stuff again can help reinforce the ideas.
So we have these lists of numbers, Xs and Ys.
We want to know which of these snippets, code snippets,
are going to evaluate to true.
So which ones do we think?
I think the first one.
First one, okay.
Let's talk through it.
So the first one, let's actually tell us why you think.
Okay well.
Talk about what happens.
In my head, what happens is XS Math is called the X, well it's not like, it's a weird
artwork in my head.
Let me give you a little hint.
So this is a function that we're passing to the map.
So what does it do?
I said it wasn't here last week.
Okay.
That's perfectly fine.
But what do we think it does?
Well, I was thinking it's kind of a comparing thing.
Well, it's quite literally Ys is one higher than the X function in list, or Xs function.
So it's a checking thing.
That's what this double equal is doing, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It calls the values of xs and
it compares those values plus one to the value of n ys is what I was thinking.
All right, so yes,
what I want to do though, is give you the right language to express it.
So I know you see what's going on, but figuring out how to express it.
So what happens is we take excess and we call map and when we call map we pass this function,
right?
This is a function.
And this function actually with what map does is it goes through every element of the list
and it applies that function to every element.
And it transforms each element into the result of what this function is.
So what you're talking about is this list here being one more than what's in this list
is kind of the language you use.
So each element of this list is the parallel element plus one, right?
And what's happening is MAP is actually then incrementing by one.
That's all it's doing, right?
And the result of MAP is going to also be a list.
So you're going to get a list of 2, 3, 4, 5 when you call this.
And when it compares to YS, it's going to see that they're equal.
So it's actually constructing a whole new list when you call mapping,
and then comparing that listing in splas.
What about the second one?
I guess it's also correct.
That's also going to return true.
Okay. What's different about this one?
It's the same.
The semantics are the same.
Yeah.
It means the same.
But the syntax is different obviously,
right? Because it looks different on the screen, right? But what this is, is our don't care
whatever. We're going to use the parameter once. And so this is the equivalent of saying x arrow
x plus one. The compiler compiles that to the same thing. So those two will return true.
What about this one? What does this next one do?
What does this return?
I mean, we would imagine that it takes the volumes and
header set in excess of the list and anything that doesn't meet that
requirement is taken out of the list, but everything else stays.
So it divides by one, and then, if it doesn't equal zero,
that's not added into the new list.
Divide by two, it does equal, or the remainder is zero,
so there's nothing else left over.
So then that gets added to this so it only returns two and four.
Okay.
So just to make it really, your head is in the right space.
To make it really clear, remember a filter is going to construct you a new list.
And this is a function, again.
And this function is returning Boolean.
And we call this a predicate.
That's a pretty standard term for it.
So called the random lecture last week.
So this is a predicate.
So we're saying, I'm going to keep the elements in excess.
I'm going to construct a new list,
keeping the elements that satisfy this predicate.
That's a simple way to say it in English.
But when you apply this filter, when
you execute this filter function, or this filter
method I guess if I want to really think.
When we call a filter, we're going to say...
I'm going to take my first list, my excess,
and I'm going to keep everything that is divisible by two,
even.
So we're going to end up with two and four.
New list, completely new list, two and four,
which will not be equal to this list, two, three, four, five.
So this will return false.
OK, now how about fold?
What does fold do?
It plus every atoms, like the current one and the right one.
Yes, I think I understand what you're saying.
So this is a function.
This is our combining function.
This is our zero element.
So what do we do?
We start with.
Start with zero.
If you think in your mind, we start with zero element.
We'd start with that and then we'd take each element
and we add it to the previous result.
So we start with zero.
This will actually do a fold left, which
means we're folding from the left.
So I don't remember which order it goes.
You can look at the code and see what it's doing.
But it's going.
It's processing the elements from left to right.
When it gets to the...
I can't remember where it applies the 0 element,
but it's going to...
No, it starts.
It's always combining 0 with something, right?
And so you're going to add up all the elements.
That's what this function is doing.
Bold is going to return what?
kind of type how do you look at that and know what type fold terms
age because zero is age. Because of this zero? Is that what you said? Yeah the zero element, so usually we use Z in the code. This is the type that we're
going to reduce or fold into so you notice here this type here is going to
to be the same type as this here.
This has to be an int, right?
So if I have a list of ints and I'm doing this,
I take two ints and I produce an int,
and this is also an int, then this whole thing should compile,
right?
We're going to add all this stuff up.
And our base value is going to be 0.
So just add the elements.
So this is going to produce an int and not a list.
So that cannot be equal to the list.
OK.
So I think the answer here is 1 and 2.
Snip is one answer.
There's another one.
So here we have the same function.
So we did this.
We reasoned through what these are, right?
These are all the same, looks like.
Same functions we talked about before.
So do we remember which one of these returns the list of 2
and 4?
3.
three oh we have a new one don't we yep this is just driving home the point that you can use this
don't care whatever syntax like this it means the same thing right so if I do this I should end up
with two and four both of these and so three and four should result in these evaluating the true
This last one's the same idea here.
So here, we're adding all the elements of 1, 2, 3, 4,
and getting back the sum of those elements.
So that would be an int with value 10,
and that count equal to a list.
So we should have 3 and 4.
Good question.
Yeah.
For number 5, if the lists are in different sizes,
what happens?
What does the output for x like the x-axis hold thing?
Oh, if these two lists?
Not necessarily, you already know it's going to return false.
But for that specific snippet in the back half,
what's the integers that it gets?
Well, this is always going to produce one list, not a list.
I mean one element, one.
It's going to be one int value, and not a list.
Well, yeah, but I'm saying.
Okay. I was rationalizing in my head that it would essentially,
though because it's using the x and y rate,
I equated x and y to xs and ys.
Yeah, in my head.
That's okay.
So I assumed it was taking the information from the list and then adding it,
but it's just its own separate thing.
Now this here is a function on ints,
so it's processing the elements.
Yeah.
Right. So it's taking whatever x and y it has.
So usually what's happening is one is going to contain the accumulator in one of these.
I think it's the one on the right right here.
And x is going to contain the new element that we're processing.
Getting from the source list.
And so it's going to then do this combination of ints, so
it's going to just add ints and produce an int, and
then it's going to just roll all the way up and produce an int in the int, so
there's no list over here, except for the list we start with that we're processing.
OK.
Ooh, this time our ys is now a single int with value 10.
So, we've already talked through this map.
Map is going to give us back a...
List.
Oh, you're going fast.
Filter is going to give me a list.
And this counter is also going to give me a list.
This one here is going to actually sum the list, sum the elements of the list.
And give it's going to use zero as the additive identity in this case.
We have zero for the additive identity.
So we end up with basically four plus three plus two plus one.
So, I don't remember which order it goes.
I think it goes from the left so it would actually add this way first, zero plus one
plus three.
I can't remember.
Don't quote me on that.
If you ever can't remember, one of the things I do is I'll actually show you.
If I can't remember, this is kind of a useful thing.
I'm going to just paste this.
So there's my list.
And I'm going to start messing with this code here.
So there's my fold and I got 10, but what I like to do sometimes is, I'll go, yeah,
I'm going to just, you can, by the way, you can do braces anytime.
You can also do this, but to keep it clear I'm going to use braces.
So anytime you can use parens you can use braces.
All right, so now I'm going to take x, y.
And every time I do the addition,
I'm going to actually print out what it does.
$x plus $y equals $x plus y.
I'm going to print it out and then I'm going to return x plus y.
And now I'm going to close the brace.
So by doing these braces here, that, you can actually use the braces in place of the, of the friends there.
You could also put a colon here and leave off the braces.
That should work well.
So this time what I got out was this little, it's telling me what order it's doing.
So now I know it's processing from the left.
So I've just confirmed my understanding.
We're processing from the left.
It starts with the zero element zero.
That's why zero shows up in the X parameter there.
Zero plus one equals one, and then it returns that.
But then the full function is now invoking.
it's taking that 1, it's like holding the result in that space, and passing it back in as the new x
for the next L. And then it does 1 plus 2, gets 3, passes the 3 in for the new x for the next L.
So this is why I do this sometimes when I'm not sure if I need to know. Usually when we're dealing
with faults, we don't need to know. We just are like, oh, I have a collection of values,
and I need to sort of squish it down into 1. So I'm going to just fold it. That's why I call it
So snippet 5 is the answer.
Okay.
Ooh.
Now we have a string.
Also, by the way, we'll cover this a little bit more later.
But when you have a fold, internally fold-on collection is going to do fold left.
That's why it's left.
That's also part of why I didn't remember that,
because I wasn't thinking about that detail.
So in this case, we're going to do the same thing,
except, well, let's look at all the functions.
Map is going to give me back a list.
It's going to do the addition.
This map is going to do the same integer addition that we had before.
This filter is going to filter out anything that's not divisible.
That's not evenly divisible by two or not a multiple of two.
This one is going to do the same as that.
So these are all going to be lists and we're dealing with strings.
So I think the answer is going to be here.
But let's talk about what's happening here.
So we're folding left again.
We're getting the string 0.
So this X parameter, what type is this X parameter going to be?
Based on what we've seen.
Do you think it's an int?
Yeah.
Why do you think it's an int?
Because it's the element.
It is the atom of the list.
And the Y is the result of the previous function.
Okay. So we're going to test out your idea.
And I can do that by just saying, hey, I'm telling you this has to be an int.
What's this type, then, in your world?
Well, a string.
String.
Nope.
Doesn't compile.
No.
And I knew that. That's why I went this way.
So the 0 element, because full, okay.
So because fold is internally going to call fold left,
0 element is a string.
So the left argument is going to be a string.
It's going to put this.
Remember when we did it before, we
had the 0 plus the integer 0.
And it put that in x, remember?
If we look back up there, it put the 0 in x
the beginning. So it's the same idea except this is now going to be strings over here,
x is going to be strings. And so, the correct way to think about this is to change this
up to be a string and then this y has to be an int instead. So... and it doesn't like
that. Why does it not like that? It doesn't even compile, an example from the image.
That.
R, int, or, to me.
So it's giving me the sum type thing.
Well, what happens if we just get rid of the?
If I get rid of the type annotations?
Yeah.
That's what those are called, type annotations.
No, it gives me int or string 0 1 2 3 4.
I don't know why, it's not doing...
So I guess it's not...
What happens if I do this?
I'm gonna force it to be a string.
Oops, dollar.
Oops, I need that.
There.
X2 string.
Oh, it's trying to do string concatenation.
That's why.
It's not automatically calling y.toString.
So, actually, I'm going to change it.
It doesn't need to call x.toString.
It needs to call...
It needs to do that.
No.
Oh, because I have to take...
Oh, wait.
Why?
I didn't try this out at all.
Y int.
Oh, but it's going to...
I'm going to just change up the...
I'm gonna have to play around this at home, so if I say x plus,
I can just do that, because the intention was to do string
Compatiation.
Oh, something doesn't like this. What type does it want, but why does it want this time?
It doesn't like any of my typing annotations at all.
Okay.
We're gonna do this.
Now I'm saying to the computer, you will not control me.
I will understand what you're doing.
Watch this.
is x.getClass.
Take that computer.
x is x.getClass, y is y.getClass.
So getClass comes from Java, and I'm telling it to tell me.
And I'm just going to return x plus 1.
So this time, I'm going to just keep the function that I'm
passing in here returning the same thing as I did before.
But I'm going to get some information about it.
What is it?
Value plus is not a member.
So the whole thing just never worked.
OK.
All right, so then instead of that,
I will not be in control by the computer,
I will return units.
And of course, I can't do that because I need an int or string.
Empty string.
Well, I'm going to, does it take a string?
Oh, maybe?
It wants an int or string.
So if I do x plus y, type annotated int or string.
I can force it, I think, to be that.
Value plus, and it's not a number of, oh.
X dot, two string, plus.
This is gonna drive me nuts.
There, now it did something.
So X is class java.lang.string,
Y is class java.lang.integer.
That's what I would expect.
So for some reason I'm getting this sum type,
I'm gonna have to go home and think about that.
That's gonna drive me a little crazy.
But I was able to coerce it into doing what I want.
So anyway, this is a string.
I wonder if these slides were developed with Scala Tube?
I bet you behaved differently in Scala Tube.
That's probably what it is.
I'll have to try that out.
So snippet five should be the answer.
have fun with that. Okay, process a list of numbers. I'm not gonna play with the types
of this one. So, here we have a list of numbers. Here we have a string. Notice our string has
like commas in between the elements of the source. Or I guess the characters. A comma
y is a character but it's got the numbers are there.
This is gonna give me back a list of events.
We know that from before.
This is also gonna give me back a list of events.
This is gonna also give me back a list of events,
only the ones that are evenly divisible by two.
Same here, so this one is not a list of events.
So we can eliminate one through four.
We have this here, okay.
So what happens when we call fold?
So we call fold, remember that this is going to be a fold left,
we're going to process from the left.
So this comma is going to appear in the beginning.
So if we say, well, it's good, I should say,
this comma will start out as the first x.
So we'll say x dot two string plus y, so we should have comma with a y after it.
I think the answer is I think this one is false.
This one here, oh, okay.
First thing we do is we map each xs value, each int value.
We turn it into a string and then we add the comma at the end.
Okay, and then we call fold, so
now we're gonna process each of those strings.
So in your mind, you've now converted this to a string where you added this
into a string where you've added the comma on the end.
Now you call fold and you start with an empty string and
then you're gonna take that and concatenate it with y.
I think this means the two string value of y.
So this should give you an empty string at the beginning followed by x1,
the string 1 with a comma at the end, and then 2, 3, 4.
So I think you're gonna get 6 is gonna be the correct answer.
Okay, so this one's a variation.
So again, list of ints, list of ints, list of ints, same logic as before.
So we're down to these three.
This one here is like the one we said before.
It's going to do a comma, but it's going to keep all of the elements.
There's no filtering, right?
So we should, in this case, that one we can eliminate because it would include all the
elements.
Okay.
I don't have those.
So now, first I'm going to filter out all of the things that are not divisible by two,
and then I'm going to map the thing, each element, to a two-string followed by a comma,
And then I'm going to fold.
We look at this one.
Is this the same?
Are these two the same?
So we have a don't care whatever pattern, we have a don't care whatever pattern but
notice x arrow x if we just replace with a single underscore, that's syntactic sugar
for this.
So so far we're the same, right?
Yeah.
And then here we have a fold, we have this, Z element,
which is the single string with a comma, and then we have this,
which is syntactic sugar for that.
So these two are actually semantically the exact same.
Does everybody see that?
This here is we have an X and a Y, and we combine them by doing this plus,
which in this case is going to be string concatenation, or should be.
Okay.
And so here, this is like a shorthand for saying this.
That's why I call it syntactic trigger.
It's just, I guess, a little bit less junking on the screen
for you to look at.
So I think the answer here is going to be six and seven.
So you can see that by noticing that the first step is this
filtering.
So that gets you halfway there.
Then you have to just sort of process through in your mind what happens here.
But if you do that for each of these, since they are the same,
you just have to do it once.
Okay, so that was our little one.
That was fun, wasn't it?
We're gonna start this topic.
this is my pride and joy so I gave a talk at the Chicago area Scala meetup but it was 2022
they haven't had a meetup in a long time and this that talk turned into this so there's still a
video on the webpage of the website of a different set of slides that I completely lost and I don't
I don't know how I did that.
I should check if Andy still has that.
But I created a whole new slide deck for the course
to cover this idea.
So what we're going to do now, is we're
going to look at folds, but we're
going to now look at how strictness and folds
can work together to make better, more interesting folds.
Actually, I have a question.
Does the fold function fold left or fold right?
Ah, that will be answered in this set of slides.
So the answer is the fold will actually do a fold left, but we'll see why that is as we go through this.
Okay.
So how are we going to apply the concepts of strictness and non-strictness to folds?
How can we use that to our advantage?
So we'll motivate the concept of lazy lists, which I mentioned a little while ago,
and infinite collections, which you can also think of as streams.
What's a stream? Does anybody know?
Just think in general. Have you been exposed to streams before?
My introduction to programming class was C,
and then we did C++ the next year.
I remember when C++ you had to include, you had to do pound include.
Iostream was to get streams.
I don't know if you remember, but in C++, you may have seen this where you have like
a C out, and then there's this thing here, and then you can print out, like, hello.
And then usually you would do EMDL for N-line, something like that.
So this comes from the iostream library.
So io is input-output, iostream.
So streams are when you have data and you don't know what the data is, it's not like
loaded in memory, you might be connected to a network and pulling data off of a network
socket and it might be...
You don't know when the socket's going to close.
So this idea does relate to that kind of conceptually.
So we'll talk about that.
And then we have more purely functional folds.
So there's a language out there called Haskell,
which I was learning about four years ago.
I kind of stopped because I focused a little more on Scala.
But Haskell has a different way of defining folds.
And we're going to look at that.
And then we're going to talk about delegating execution
control to a fold without sacrificing efficiency
or program termination.
This was the big aha for me.
And I'll talk you through kind of my whole thought process of how I got here.
We'll take a very simple example.
We have this list of integers.
And I'm going to just do this 0 to 10,000 and call toList on it.
And if I want to sum those, then this is my old school.
like if I'm in Java, if I'm in C, I use mutability.
That's what this var is.
So I iterate through the integers,
and I just keep adding to my accumulator.
And so if you do this with that list, you get this value here.
So we've been talking about folds,
So if we have a list of events, we can call fold on it.
We can use zero as our zero element,
we can use this underscore, plus underscore, to do that addition.
So we're passing this as a function, this is just shorthand for a function,
that x, comma, y, and a two arrow and then x plus y.
So we can do it functionally this way.
So if we have a fold left, we can actually, instead of calling fold, we can call fold left.
In this case, I just did 0 to 10.
So sum l, I'm going to do this fold from the left and get 55.
And over here, I'm going to do fold from the right and get 55.
In fold right, what would happen is we would process the elements.
So the zero element would be added to the 10, and then it would roll on back and
process each element going backwards.
I say backwards because I'm thinking of right as the end of the list and left as the left.
So which argument in the function pass is the accumulator?
So we kind of covered this before.
This one's gonna be the accumulator in fold left and this one's gonna be the accumulator
right.
And then the question naturally arises is how is fold implemented, right?
So we asked the question, so this was the question that was asked on online, and how
How does Scala implement fold?
So, oh, and what I did here was I did what your homework does, right?
You know how your homework has the three question marks which throws a not implemented error?
I did that because I was like, I want to know how fold is implemented.
And I know that I'm going to get an exception if I, if I can either throw the exception
or I can actually use the three question marks.
But in this case, I see that if I look through the stack trace,
I see that here's my list.
OK, so here's the list.
And here's where I'm calling fold left.
And you see this is linear seek ops, linear seek ops, j function.
I show you this because this is actually how I'll actually do it.
So if I go to a file that's in a project here,
and I'm going to make up some stuff.
And I'll just put it in.
This has nothing to do with your homework,
but I'm just putting it here.
I'll just create a new file.
That's OK.
Scala class, I'll call it an object, and I'll just call it main.
So, I meant to say object, I do this all the time.
I say class when I mean object, and then I just have to change it, okay.
So I'm going to say val xs with int equals, and I'm just going to do that for a moment,
and I'm going to call xs, and all I'm doing is playing around with the compiler, right?
So I want to know where fold is implemented.
So what I did,
And I'm going to show you a trick.
Extends app.
If I do that, it will make the whole thing a main program
instead of having to type all that stuff
to make it a main program.
So I'm going to do that.
And actually, why don't I just say we'll just
use what's in the code.
So 0 to 10 dot 2 list.
And if I say, excess.fold, 0, this is the colon syntax that I can use if I want.
So that should work.
Oh, and I don't want to do that.
I want to actually throw an exception because that's what I'm doing.
I'm just so used to the other example.
So, you see in the comment I wrote, show me the call stack involved in executing this
function.
So, this is a trick I use as a programmer all the time, when I'm not sure.
I want to know and I want to know fast without having to navigate through all the code.
Until j and most of our IDEs in the world will do,
let's assume, let's hope this runs,
is it will throw that exception.
Of course, I did this with Scala 2 once,
so I wonder if this is gonna work?
I think we did it with Scala 3 though.
I think it fixed it.
So, we're gonna have to wait for the compiler,
because it's slow.
There it goes.
Alright.
So we end up with this.
Hey, what happened?
Oh, it could not find class main.
Okay, fine.
Let's rebuild the document.
Maybe something.
Let's say building.
There, there it is.
Okay, I don't know why it did that.
This is exception in initialize.
Oh, it's, yeah.
Exception and initializer error is just because it's calling this main function that I'm defining
by extending this app thing.
So that's what that means.
So yeah.
So this is what we saw.
So we're in foldLeft, and if we keep going,
this is our list foldLeft.
And foldLeft is going to be defined.
Let's see here's a foldLeft.
Let me show up.
It is the same.
Line 79.
It must be, that's weird.
It must be going into linear CCOPS.
Okay, so this is me just being an experienced programmer
looking at the output and figuring out what's doing.
So the point of all this, there is a point to all this.
Ultimately our fold left is gonna be defined,
our fold is going to be defined in here.
And actually, I'll check one last thing.
Let's just go to fold.
That's what I was looking for.
In iterable once, it says fold,
and it's got this junk here.
Okay, so that's where I'm going to get my fold definition.
And you'll see that somebody asked,
Is fold calling fold left?
Is fold calling left?
It's actually going to be defined as calling fold left.
So if you keep going, you keep looking around
and asking these questions, you'll
find inside the scala library the implementations.
So fold left, there's a lot of junk here.
We're going to talk about these pluses
and these little arrow things that you see here.
Those are called type bounds and this is called variance, but we'll do that in much later
lecture, so don't worry about that.
But you'll see fold left here and notice what it's doing.
It's using a var and it's using a while loop.
So we just got through talking about how these are sort of higher order functions.
This is higher order programming.
We're doing functional programming.
And yet under the covers the Scala language here is doing this looping with a var.
Over here with the fold right, it's even more interesting.
We have, first we reverse, and then we're looping with a var.
And if we call, look at reverse, this is what reverse looks like.
And again, this may be a slightly older version of Scala than if you were to do this on your
own today.
You might see something different.
But ultimately, you're gonna see this kind of thing.
You're gonna have vars and while loops.
You're calling reverse, so you're calling this whole thing.
You're iterating through all the elements once and then you're iterating through all
the elements again.
If you have a lot of elements, it's not really desirable.
So what I did here is I put these little comments, this is an expression, American slang, lipstick
on a pig.
It's like when you have something that's like ugly and you're trying to make it better,
but it's still to me as a programmer, this is not intellectually satisfying because I'm
not really doing a fold in the way that we would like to be we're just doing
looping. And then over here I said lipstick on a pig airbrush because we
have two loops so it's even worse. So here's why so we have fars we have while
this is glorified iteration and it's implemented directly in Scala so in the
language in the library it's right there it's not even at them at the machine
code language. Now ultimately in the virtual machine, it is doing looping, right? It is,
there's jumps and there's all these things and I don't care about that. Like, I'm working
in a higher level language. I would like my, since we have support for things in Scala,
I would like support for functional programming in Scala. I would like this to be more purely
functional and it's not. And one thing that really stuck with me when I was like first
learning about folds I have friends who were like Eric you gotta learn folds
they're the most awesome things like 10 years and I was like I'm not sold
because folds and Scala don't allow me to abort my processing early. I have a
really big collection there's no way to avoid iterating over every element with
the way we have defined folds with these iterations here. So every time we
execute a fold, that particular piece of code
executes in linear time in terms of the length of the list.
And then this other thing, fold write, we have vars,
we have while times two with the reverse call,
and it's just more glorified iteration over every element.
So my friends were like, learn folds.
And I said, why?
This is not giving me much.
So here's an illustration of what happens when I try to do find and find is, this is
like I'm finding a particular element.
And this is linear find, this is not binary.
Right?
If we did binary search, it would be more efficient.
We're not doing that for this discussion.
We're going to walk through the list and we're going to find the element.
So this is our old school iteration.
This is what it looks like.
You start with a key.
You're trying to find the index where that key exists,
and then you use this loop control, this i,
and then you use this while loop.
I have this special condition here to if I get a minus one.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I have to be before the end of the list,
and as long as I haven't found the result,
then I wanna keep executing.
Otherwise, I'm gonna exit the loop early.
That's what I wanna do.
If you can imagine why I would do this,
I might have a really, really, really long list.
And if I'm looking for a number
that occurs early in the list,
in this case, these are not sordid.
They are shuffled, but they could be shuffled.
And if they're shuffled,
we don't know where the result lives.
So in this case, I'm gonna find this seven pretty quick,
right, because it's in the beginning.
But if I shuffled the list
and it was really, really huge
that I had pulled in off network or something like that.
Well, I might have to go through this whole list and
I might want to stop early.
So this is me saying, I want to stop early if I found it.
That's all.
So what we see down here is just the finding like if I were
to execute it in the REPL for you and it would find the element, sorry,
I jumped ahead.
it would find the element at 8 because we're 0 indexed,
so it would find 7.
Again, contrived, because I'm not shuffling the data,
and it's a small amount of data.
So one of my friends actually asked this.
I show you this so that you never, if you ever see it,
don't do it and take it out of your code.
Why can't I just break instead of that extra condition here?
Remember that extra condition?
Wouldn't it be nice if I could just say break like I
can in Java right one of my friends said he was sitting in San Francisco and I was
here in Chicago we were on a call and he was like but we do have this in Scala
and I was like no we don't and he was like yeah we do and so what he found was
this thing so you can import this Scala util control and there is this loop
loop.breakable, this is actually taking a function and you can call loop.break. This
is a way to get that, but it's implemented using exceptions. And programmers tend to
frown upon using exceptions to control execution, so you don't really want to do control flow
with exceptions.
So what's actually happening is,
when you call loop.break, it's throwing an exception.
And then breakable is catching that exception,
and returning.
So that's how it's getting out of the loop early.
So if I see this in your homework,
I'm not gonna be happy with you, so don't do it.
There's always, well, actually no,
nobody's actually done it yet,
but I'm always worried that somebody isn't really
paying attention to the lecture,
and then they go read the slides,
and then they're like, oh, look, I can do this.
So I'll know who you are if you do that.
So yeah, using exceptions for control flow
is considered very bad.
So as programmers, that's something you should know.
So don't do it.
OK.
So we're going to do this.
We're going to do a find with a fold left.
So you can type this code in, or you can paste it
I'm looking for number 42.
Basically what I got here is I'm using a tuple.
And my tuple I'm saying is minus 1.
This is you have to sort of like read through it to sort of make sense of it.
Remember before I had minus 1 was the index that I was looking for.
So I started out with minus 1, and then I'm starting at the 0 element.
And then I'm, now as a fold left, I'm going to, this is my 0 element.
So that's going to appear here on the left side, right.
And then over here is the new element.
I'm using the underscores because I don't actually
need to bind to a variable for each case.
So what I'm saying is, well, if I haven't found it,
that's what this if is, this k is what I'm looking for.
If I haven't found it, then I want to return i plus 1 and k.
If I do find it, then I'm going to say, oh, OK.
So this part here, this i plus 1 is returning the next.
It's like doing the i plus plus, like in a loop, like in Java.
But here, what I'm saying is, if n equals key, well, OK,
that means I found the 42, right?
And so at index i is where I found it.
So if I ever get something that is not minus 1,
then I'm just carrying on through the rest of the list.
preserving the result. And then over here what this is doing is it's saying, okay,
if all of these other cases fail, so I haven't found it yet and I didn't match so I keep
going and I keep minus one. That's like not changing the result when you have the loop.
Like if we look back at the loop I'm just taking the loop from over here and actually
was the previous one, I mean taking the, well, no it's more like that one.
I'm taking the loop from over here and I'm just saying, well IDX,
this case is called IDX, it didn't change.
So that's what this last case is.
All right, so there, so that's how we do find left this way.
But I did this to illustrate that,
even though I found the result at, remember I didn't shuffle, right?
I found the result at 42 but I still had to go through the whole list.
So this is less than satisfying to me.
So loop control is delegated completely to ListsFoldLeft function.
And I found the element early but I still had to go through all 10,000 elements.
And the question is can we do better?
And this is a good place to stop for our break.
We'll come back at 7.30 and pick this up, get through the second half of these slides,
And you'll see how we try to use recursion and why that's better in one way but not so good in another way.
And then we'll look at how to make the folds even better.
So take a break and see you at 7.30.
I'm not sure.
Thank you.
Take a look.
You're not kidding me, you're not kidding me?
It's not a problem.
Professor, I'm missing something.
Most of the classes were empty tonight.
Did I not get the memo?
Was there something closing?
Are they closing?
Are they not doing class tonight?
I mean, there's a couple classes over there that are usually full and they're empty, and
I'm like, oh my gosh, what's going on?
I have no idea.
I checked my email, so I didn't see anything.
Okay.
You don't mind me asking, what class?
This is 447, Concepts and Programming Languages.
Awesome.
Are you adjunct or full-time?
Adjunct.
Same here.
I'm just teaching the Capstone.
I'm Eric.
What's your name?
I'm Paul Reskowitz.
Eric Frederick.
Nice to meet you.
I teach the Capstone, which is fairly basic.
Oh, cool.
This is mostly scholars stuff.
Yeah, and I like the content of it's more.
It's educational.
Capstones are just kind of work on your group project.
Yeah, work on your projects, yeah.
And here's some other things you're going to do in your career.
Yeah.
It was nice to meet you.
Nice to meet you, yeah.
Thank you.
Ah.
Okay.
so
One more time.
Thank you.
Shh.
So, I'm going to make a large set of pieces of a piece of paper.
I'm going to go ahead and go ahead and press the camera.
So, let's see.
so
Thank you.
So...
So, after you go out of here, you can see this one.
I'm going to go out of here.
I'm going to go out of it.
Yeah, I know, I don't want to talk about it.
Well, I have to use this method.
I'm going to go ahead and see if I can do it.
I will see you in the video.
.
Okay.
All right, let's pick it up.
So this is where we left off.
And the key point here is that I found number 42,
which should be pretty early in this list.
But again, we don't know in a real production code
what order these would be in.
But for the sake of argument, we should return early
if we find it early.
So that would be nice.
But what we had to do is we had to go through the entire list.
And that's what you get with a fold using Scala folds.
So what happens if we try to do recursion?
And for a long time, this was my go-to solution,
because I was not thinking about how I could make folds better.
I was just thinking about, I want to abort the execution
as soon as I can.
So this is how I can do it.
So here's a find function.
It's actually I guess a method because it's def.
We're looking for a key, and we have a list that we're looking in.
And we have this search function.
We start by calling search.
We're using zero as our i.
So this i is going to just tell us where we are in the list.
And we've got our list.
And so we start off with passing the whole list,
And then we're going to do this pattern match thing.
So when we get to the end of the list, we're going to say we didn't find it.
Right?
If that makes sense.
So we return minus 1.
If, on the other hand, we have a head and a tail,
and the head of the list is equal to the key that we're looking for,
then I'm going to return i, and I can stop.
I no longer have to process the rest of the list.
Okay.
If, on the other hand, I don't find it,
I have to keep going.
And so I call search recursively with the rest of the list.
So this is a pattern we're used to seeing with recursion in Scal.
And again, I'm incrementing i here because I'm going to the next element of the list,
so it's just keeping track of where it was.
Okay, so if I call this, I find 42 and
And it just returns 42, so it doesn't illustrate any more.
But you can just see, since there's no recursive call,
it's not continuing to plod through the rest of the list.
All right, so I can abort the search when I'm done.
And the compiler, because of this tail rack,
the compiler will actually turn this into a loop.
But this is at the compiler level.
This isn't in the Scala language.
It isn't in the Scala library.
It's down... the compiler is creating the bytecode, and it's doing instructions at a low level.
And I don't care about that. Like that has to happen because if you want to run a program on a computer, you've got to do that.
But I like that happening after the compiler.
But the compiler doing that for me, and I don't have to be okay.
But I'm still responsible for the execution control.
So me, as the programmer of this function, I had to decide whether I was going to call the recursive function or not, and so I'm in charge of that.
So is there a way, the question naturally occurs, is there a way to get the best of both?
I can delegate, can I delegate execution control and get this efficiency that I'm looking for?
So if I use folds from the standard scholar collections, you can't get that.
All right.
So if I have this here, and I convert this to a list,
notice that what's happening here,
one to int max value in this carens,
that actually this two thing is going to create a range.
A range is actually going to be lazy, lazy, non-strict, same thing.
So that's going to be non-strict.
But once I call toList,
I'm going to actually have to realize every element of the list I have to go through,
and I have to compute the model, right?
So if I try to do that, if I go from one to the max value, and
I try to convert that to a list, I'm gonna get an out of memory error.
So a way to illustrate this, actually, is to just do this part first.
So if I go to the REPL.
So I get a scholar collection immutable range inclusive.
And it prints out this way, range one, two, and
then this two billion number, right?
And it's lazy, like I said before, it's non-strict.
So it knows something about where it begins and where it ends,
but it doesn't need to know every single element.
So it's not realizing those elements.
But once I call that to list,
this will run for a bit.
Spoiler alert, it's what happens on the slide.
That's not the slide.
It's that out of memory here.
Java heap space.
So the reason it says that is because it's trying to create all of these objects on the
heap.
And eventually, you will use up all the space in the heap because there's so many integers
there are from one to the max value.
It's even half of the space that you're trying to fill up.
Because of course you have minus, you have min value of right now,
negative infinity, but not even this will be able to be held in memory.
So our Scala standard collections are gonna be strict generally.
Which is why earlier when we had that example on the screen,
that when we called the method tail, and
I said that was strict because it's implemented that way.
So that means that all elements of the collection are evaluated, their values actually exist
in memory, they're actually taking up space in memory.
So what if I decided to try to make the list non-strict, what if I tried to go for something
that was more lazy?
What would happen?
So Scala Collections has something for this, it's called a lazy list.
And a lazy list is inspired by other functional programming languages.
They used to actually, in Scala 2, they called it stream.
So that's related to this idea of a stream we talked about.
Let's flip over here, did it eventually.
It finally died, so Java heap space.
So that was just to show you what it is.
So this is what happens when I do this kind of thing.
So if I say lazy list stuff from 1, it's going to give me that.
It's gonna say this not computed thing.
This not computed is just an indicator to you,
if you're looking at the two-string output,
that it's a list of some unknown length.
And it hasn't even figured out what the head is.
Like it's just, remember how we talked about non strictness?
So these are just expressions that sit there waiting to be a value.
They're thunks waiting to be a value.
The next one lazy1.tail.head, well if I call .tail,
I have to evaluate the head, and then I get the next one, the tail.
And the tail is not evaluated until I call head.
In order to determine what the head is, I have to evaluate the head.
So that's why I'm going to get a two out.
Now if I try to see what lazy list one is now, lazy1,
That's this one here.
I'm gonna get lazy list not computed,
because it actually had to realize these in order to do what I told it to do.
So it had to actually go and figure out what is the first element.
And then on the tail, what is the first element of the tail?
But it left the rest of it not computed, because it wasn't called for,
it wasn't used yet, it wasn't needed.
So we call this memoization.
One and two are memoized, so once they're created, they're kept around.
This is also like similar to the Scala keyword lazy that we talked about a while back where
it doesn't evaluate it until it gets requested.
Okay, so if I do a lazy list of five, if I say lazy1.take5, it's actually going to...
it's going to actually take the initial expression and use it over again but then stop it after
So it's keeping that all that those parameters,
it's those that idea is keeping in memory.
But it's a completely different lazy list.
So it's not computed.
That's why this is not computed for me.
So if I.
Do a list of five, and
I say a list of one, two, three, four, five.
Oh, that right.
So the code here, sorry.
I'm reading this as if it's the code.
What I'm doing is I'm saying, I took this lazy list of five,
and it's got five elements.
And I call two lists on it.
Well, that's a finite list.
So it'll produce a list.
And this will all be utilized in memory, so a regular list.
And now if I take lazy list of five again,
this time it will show me lazy lists 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Because in order to produce this list,
it actually had to go and evaluate the first five elements
in order to two-list for five of these.
So that's what's going on here.
But you see 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 are mammalized.
So this gives rise to the idea that lazy list might be infinite.
Could go on forever.
And it's related to the concept of a stream, as I said before.
So now what happens if I try to take this lazy list
and I try to do this find example I've been doing
with a fold left.
I'm introducing a little bit of syntax
that you don't know yet, this opaque type.
So we've got, when I was building the slides,
it got to be a little bit crazy
to be looking at all of these tuples and i's and K's,
and I just said, well, let's make the index called index.
So that's what this is.
This is Scala stuff that basically just lets me
wrap an integer in this type,
is opaque type they call it in Scala3,
call it index, so now I can use that as a type.
So I'm defining an apply method,
which I can wrap an integer,
and if I have a special,
I'm gonna have a special version of not found.
So this corresponds to what we were doing before
when we were looping when we were using minus one,
meaning that I didn't find it.
So, if I have my lazy list here,
and this is another piece of Scala
that you may not have seen yet,
So zip with index, what that's going to do,
it's going to take each element and associate it
with the index.
So if I do that, let's actually put it in.
Oh, you know what?
Actually, we'll show you here.
So each of these lines is like processing each line.
So I get lazy ints, which is going to be not computed.
So this is an infinite list from zero.
That's what that means.
And I have my key that I'm looking for is seven.
This will say I've defined object index,
that's this bit here.
Actually it's probably the lines four through six
and then it will say,
oh it didn't say that it, oh it did, yeah.
So val not found is an index minus one, okay.
So that's just telling me, it's printing out
what happened here, like what I did here.
So now I'm gonna create my indexed ints.
So what I get is this lazy list not computed
And this time I have int int.
I guess it must be printing that out.
I would like it to say that it's type index, but apparently it's not.
I may have to actually do something to change that.
But it should be the index here.
Point is that it's a lazy list, and it's not computed.
And even that is going to give me, when I do fold left at line 11, I'm going to get an out of memory error.
So why do we think that's happening?
Well, we said that with our standard Scala folds, we're still going to process every element.
It's actually going to hold all of this stuff in memory.
So it's going to go and it's going to have to construct all this stuff in a heap and
eventually go run out of space.
So this didn't help us any, just by throwing a lazy list at the problem, didn't help us
at all.
So, we are still trying to go through the entire lazy list.
Bad news.
Let's try this same idea, but let's do it with a full write.
so this just all gets flipped around as fold right.
So again, lazy inc, not computed.
He's going to be seven,
of course we have to define the object index again,
we have to define the not found again.
Here we have indexed ints,
and we start off with not computed.
And here I also got an outer memory error.
Remember what happened with fold right.
We immediately call reverse,
So we have to reverse the lazy list, and then maybe it has a reverse that is lazy, but then we have to actually, oh, when it calls reverse, no, it has to actually process each element of the lazy list, right?
So it's going to construct all that in memory.
So not any better.
So still trying to go through the entire lazy list.
Okay. So let's look at how lazyList defines fold.
So we have fold left here.
And if I call fold left, and I have is empty,
I'm going to get the z, and otherwise I'm going to go to the tail.
So it means I have to evaluate the lazily defined tail,
and then I have to fold left.
That's how it's defined.
Fold write is going to do this.
So it's going to call reverse.
So what's reversed?
Reverse is going to, oh gosh, it's going to go right to a list.
A regular, non-lazy list.
Okay, well that's why we're going to get out a memory error, right?
No good.
And then, if we look at fold,
the fold is defined in a trait called iterable once ops.
and that's going to immediately call fold left,
which is going to give us this implementation in this case.
So we have, again, var iteration while
continual evaluation of tail
while retaining each con cell in memory,
and it's not quite what we want.
It doesn't buy us much.
The parameters are strictly evaluated by default
in most languages, as we've seen in Scala.
They're strictly evaluated.
But in Haskell, and this is why Scala has,
it's call by name,
because it has its roots
in the functional programming paradigm,
and even though it also has object-oriented features,
and that's what we're used to
because we're mostly coming out of Java land,
in Haskell, our parameters
are not going to be strictly defined by default.
So let's try making parameters nonstrict.
So this is what a Haskell-style fold left looks like.
So in my journey learning functional programming,
I reached a point where I was studying Haskell,
and I realized that the way Haskell was doing things
was fundamentally different than this mess I had in Java
with strict parameters and I was developing sort of the intuition for it.
So if I look at Haskell, this is what a fold L looks like.
So I still have my same stuff defined here.
Fold L, so we're gonna use the Haskell names here.
And this is just a depth, so I'm just defining a method in my session here or
in my object.
And notice there's a lot of this stuff in the syntax.
So I'm taking a function that has a, what is this?
A call by name parameter that produces a b,
so it doesn't actually have to evaluate the b.
And then I take another parameter, that's an a,
and I produce a b. So I'm going to combine this b.
I'm going to, sorry, I'm going to combine this a
with the zero element.
And yeah, I guess I'm going to combine these two things to produce a new B,
that's why my return type here is B.
Notice I'm using the variable name C for the zero element, as usual.
And here's my lazy list argument, so
what I'll do is I'll do pattern matching, right?
So this is how we do pattern matching with lazy list,
it's a little uglier than what we're used to with nil, and
with regular lists we're used to just the cons.
You have to use these funny things here to make it work.
So this pattern match will work.
So if I get to the empty list, I'm going to produce the z element.
So I'll finally evaluate the z element.
And otherwise, I'm going to call foldL immediately,
passing the function.
So notice the first parameter is the function.
And then the z element goes here.
And in order to get to the z element, I'm passing f of z x.
So see my function f of z x, I'm actually going to pass z for this one and then x for this one.
So if I want to do my find left example, what happens?
I'm going to implement a little helper function called check here.
And what check's gonna do is it's gonna take this find rest.
Okay, check.
Yeah, so the find rest is gonna be a lazy parameter that's gonna produce some index,
right, that's what I'm looking, I'm looking for what index it is.
And then my next element is gonna be this here, and I'm gonna say okay,
I'm gonna pattern match.
If I found it, if the key is equal to n, I'm gonna return i,
Otherwise, I'm going to just call find rest, which will be this thunk that I pass.
So that's why this was passed here.
So we say fold l passing check, that's the function that corresponds to this.
Notice the function is defined here, lines two through five.
So I'm passing that function in fold l, which is over here.
And then my zero element is not found.
And then I pass the index it's here.
So if I do this, so I'm defining object index.
This is showing you what happens when I execute the code here.
I'm defining not found to be minus one.
And here's me defining the foldL function and the findLeft function.
And it doesn't print out that thing about the helper function.
Check.
So here's my initial lazy ints.
This is down here.
lazy list from zero and indexed ints.
I'm just mapping there to pass,
to have the index next to it.
And I would still get an out of memory error.
So, so far the Haskell style fold left with
this non strict stuff isn't helping me at all.
That was my hope, but it didn't work.
So, so far no better.
So now we'll do a Haskell style fold right.
So this time, fold r follows the way Haskell defines it.
If you notice, so the fold l is the first thing that gets called.
But if you notice here, fold r, we actually are calling f,
and notice f has curry parameters.
so f, this is my f, period parameters, it takes two parameter lists, right?
So x and then it's passing this whole thing as an expression, as a thunk.
So with find right, I have the same thing.
I had to flip the order here, right?
But I have the same thing.
So if I follow through how this goes, so I define object index,
I define my not found, I define my fold r,
and I define my find right.
There's my lazy list of integers, which is lazy in memory,
and there's my lazy list of indexed integers,
and I call find right, and this time,
I get a much more satisfying answer.
I get the answer is 7.
If you remember, when we tried it with the left,
we got an out of memory error.
When we try it with the right, we get an answer.
And the only difference between standard Scala collections, really, and this definition, so the way that they do fold, is we're using this non-strictness and this laziness in this function.
So we'll see why, coming up, like how it sort of processes.
But first, I'll just point out there's no elements we visit unnecessarily.
We don't end up with that out of memory error.
And it's much better, so it's much more satisfying.
So this is why my friends were telling me to learn folds.
And now I started to learn and started
to understand better why this is desirable.
So why does foldR work better?
So what happens when I call findRight?
So I'm here in line 7, line 10.
It's actually going to print out each one, I think.
FindRight, oh there it is.
So what happens when I call?
This is me, I'm calling findRight seven index nts.
But if we look at the definition of findRight,
we can actually see how it expands.
So it immediately is going to say, let's match on the list.
And since the list is not empty, it's
going to go to this case here.
And it's going to call foldr, check not found and the list here.
Oh, wait a minute, I'm in the wrong pattern match, see what happens when I look in the
wrong place.
So let's do that again.
We're calling find right with 7 as the key and index int as pass as the laziness, and
then we're calling fold r right here at line 6, see that?
That's why I wrote fold r here, because we're actually passing the check function as we've
find the function here, passing not found as the Z.
And then I use this little notation
to just represent the list, the lazy list.
So indexed ints, I'm going to just say 0 up to whatever,
because it's going to go forever.
This notation actually comes from Haskell land.
I made that up for this slide deck.
But in Haskell, they actually would
print that out on the screen if you
had an infinite list starting with 0.
So what happens when I call fold r?
Now we're going to pattern match here.
So, our list is not empty.
So we'll immediately call f, which we passed check as our function.
So we call check, and then x is going to be that first element on the head of the lazy list.
So we'll pass that into the first argument list.
And then the second argument list is going to be this fold r expression.
And this foldR is going to be, when we call foldR recursively,
this is going to be delayed execution.
It's going to be non-strict.
So this whole thing gets passed as a thunk,
and it's never evaluated yet.
So this is what happens here.
So when I have that, that's why we have this whole thing here.
You already follow that?
We're just passing the expression.
We're not evaluating.
So then what happens?
Now check is gonna call old aria.
So now what we have is two functions
calling each other, recursively.
So it's gonna keep going
and notice it's gonna pass this same expression here.
here.
Oh, and what this is showing is the two steps at a time.
Right? So, now I've got two.
And it's – notice how it's just passing this expression that's just sitting there in memory.
It's the expression that's sitting in memory. Amazing.
So I'll keep going eventually when I get to seven, I'll find it.
In this case, when I find it,
we're gonna match on this case where the key equals n.
And we'll return i.
So that's why i just get index.7.
So we got sort of the behavior that we had when we were using tail recursion,
able to abort the execution early by leveraging this technique.
What happens when we do it with fold left though?
So same idea, but now let's just apply the fold left definition.
We do that, we'll see if we start off like this, findLeft3 with our indexed ints.
If we call findLeft, we have this defined, this function defined, but then we execute
this fold l. So it'll translate that to fold l, so fold l check not found and
then this is the value of my indexed ins. When I call fold l I'm going to match on
this case here so it will then replace with that whole thing and it will
going and it will construct this huge expression to the point where it'll run
out of memory. It'll never actually evaluate. So this is what happens with
fold left using the Haskell style fold left. We never call check. The other one
we were checking at each point. In fold R we were checking at each point. This time
we never do. The program doesn't terminate. So that's bad, fold L, in this case. So here's a
summary. We've learned about strictness and non-strictness, and I wanted to find a way to
relate them to folds, because in the larger world of functional programming, non-strictness is key
for folds. So we can leverage Scala's non-strict semantics for collections processing.
Expressions can have a value if some of their sub expressions do not.
Call by name is super useful.
Non-strictness is what allows programs to work with infinite data structures.
So when we're dealing with data that we don't know how long it is, it might go on forever,
might be consuming off of a network socket until we get an end of stream, this non-strictness
will give us a lot of power.
Non-strict folds.
So they often say, in functional programming,
fold r is often the right fold.
It works great with non-strict functions on infinite lists.
And then non-strict folds, fold l is where we use fold.
There's actually something in Haskell called fold l prime,
which they've made it so that it leverages non-strictness.
And it is useful, but I didn't go into it here.
And I don't remember the details.
but the nice thing is we can delegate execution control to our fold without sacrificing efficiency.
So that's the crux of that stuff.
And now we get to a very complicated topic,
mostly because it's eight o'clock pm and we're going to see a bunch of stuff on the screen
that's going to make your eyes pop out.
But don't panic, it's going to be okay.
If that didn't make your eyes pop out, this will.
So now we're gonna talk about formal semantics.
There's actually a course called 535,
Formal Semantics of Programming Languages.
When I was in school here,
they offered it relatively frequently,
but I think there hasn't been a lot of students
interested in it,
so they haven't been offering it lately,
although maybe I can get too interested.
I don't know.
What are we looking to do?
How are we going to unambiguously define the semantics of a programming language?
Again, the semantics is just meaning.
We talked earlier about syntax and semantics.
We're going to identify the difference between syntactic and semantic expressions in operational semantics.
We'll identify judgments and reduction rules, apply reduction rules to execute programming.
If all that sounds really abstract, hang on tight.
So here's a small program.
We're making this language up.
So our language is going to have integer expressions, statements, assignment.
Our statements are going to be assignment or statement lists or conditionals or loops.
So we're used to thinking, you know, whenever you learn a new programming language,
you want to learn about, like, well, what can I do?
How do I control the flow of the program?
Here's an example program in our made up programming language called factorial.
This should look familiar to you.
So we're just iteratively computing the factorial, right?
So we've made this up in syntax while I do and then it ends with OD.
A lot of times there are languages out there in the world that use
like the reverse of the control word, the keyword.
You see here that same idea with a headline.
Operational semantics defines meaning of programs relative to an abstract machine.
The abstract machine, so this is a reduction machine.
machine operates on a program and reduces it to its semantic quote value. And we're
gonna use this funny little character here. I had to look it up. It's called a
psi. It's a Greek letter. When you see that this is the beginning of okay we're
starting to get into math land. So all this is gonna do is be a symbol that
represents a map from variables to values. So think about Java HashMap. You
You have keys and values, right?
Something that usually you might have a string to an int
or something like that, or an int to a string.
In this case, we're going to have this just sort of abstract
notion of a map with keys and values.
And the keys are going to, the xie thing
is going to hold our map of variable names
to what the values are currently holding.
So then we're going to have a state machine.
So the state of the machine, sorry.
We're going to have a state of the machine.
So the machine is going to have this state that has a program value and the store, Xi.
So it's going to have the program for value and the store.
So this is the program and the store.
And this is the value once you've evaluated what the program means and
reduced the program to a value or reduced an expression to a value.
And then we have xi, which is our map again.
We're going to have these things called judgments.
So judgments are, if we see something like this with this double down arrow,
what's happening here is we're saying that this program reduces to this value and
this xi, this variable store that we have, is going to be reduced to xi prime.
So what does that mean?
Well, all that means is I have a map, I said that was a map.
And as I executed the program, I might have created new variables.
And I'm gonna store those variables in the map.
So we call that psi prime, because we've modified psi.
It's a pretty standard notation used in the map.
Okay, so executing program prg in state psi yields,
that's what this down arrow means.
value v and new state, new set of variables and values,
new map of variables and values, psi prime.
So then we're going to have, so those are judgments,
then we're going to also have this idea of a reduction rule.
So in our reduction rule, we're going to have a series of premises,
premise 1, 2, 3, n, up to n, whatever n is,
And we're gonna have this line and then underneath the line, we're gonna have the conclusion.
So this will be what the meaning of this is.
This is like saying these little gray bars tell you what this means.
So the conclusion follows from all the premises being satisfied.
Okay.
So if we have the language of integer expressions, so here's our syntax.
An expression can be, this is, I can't remember for sure, but there's a formal name for this,
I think it's called Bacchusnauer form.
I can't remember if this is exactly that or not.
But, this is a way to define a language, that's what we're doing here.
So, we're saying that an expression is either a number, this little pipe character means
or.
Or, it's an expression plus an expression, so this would be addition.
Or, it's an expression minus an expression.
that would be subtraction, or it's an expression times an expression,
that would be multiplication, or it's got this
parenthesis idea, which you can group things.
Or I could have an open paren, an expression, and a closed paren.
So here's an example of an expression in my,
or a couple different expressions in my language. So I have this expression
here, 2 plus 3 times 4. Here I have the group 2 plus 3.
that I'm gonna do that first and that quantity times 4. So the semantic domain
of this language is integer arithmetic. The value V is, I didn't mean to press
that, is the meaning of an expression. So for example, 2 plus 3 times 4, with you
know, 2 plus 3 quantity times 4 means 20. And we can reason about that, because if
We do this in our head, we get 5 times 4.
We do this first, and we multiply 5 times 4, and we get 20.
So that's why it means 20.
Numbers are always going to evaluate to their value.
So this is the first rule.
So if I have a number, just a plain old number 5, that's going to evaluate to the value 5.
That's what this is saying.
So this part over here is the rule num.
It's called num.
And this line here just means that there's no premises that need to be satisfied for
this to be true.
So it isn't conditional on these premises being satisfied, it's just a number always
evaluates to itself.
So if I look at this rule, this is just like before I'm using this little notation here.
This is, I'm doing an addition, right?
So this is my expression.
I have expression one plus expression two, so this is a whole expression.
Earlier on that earlier slide, it was called PRG, right?
So that's just another way to say expression.
This is an expression.
And I have this xi zero.
So xi again is my map of variables.
And I have these two question marks.
Well, okay.
So what goes in on the right side?
And before we can do that, we have to know what the premises are.
So we have to see something about E1 and something about E2, right?
So if you think about just plain old Java or Scala,
you're doing like 5 plus 3.
We're doing add, so I should probably keep it to add.
I'll do 5 times 3 in here.
So if I do that, I'm trying to do an add rule.
This is an expression, and this is an expression.
So this is my E1, and this is my E2, right?
So just by way of example, that's what this is.
So what needs to be true?
Well, E1 is going to evaluate to some value.
That's why we see V1 here.
And E2 is going to evaluate to some value.
Oh, what it's doing is it's filling it in sort of like weird.
So if I start with E1, this is where I was.
And what it just did was it filled in Xi0.
So this is our variable store.
And then I say, E1, this double arrow
is saying E1 evaluates to value V1.
And in the process of doing that evaluation,
I may have changed the variables.
You can think about that logically.
Like if you're executing a program,
it might actually do that.
So here I have E2, same idea.
This has to evaluate to something,
and I might change the variable store.
So here, one thing to note is we evaluate E1 first,
we get V1, we may have changed the variable store to get xi1.
Now we have xi1 here, we are evaluating E2,
we're going to get V2, and we're going to get xi2,
because we may be changing the variable store yet again.
So if we have that much, and if we see this,
then we can reason about what should be here in this.
And this is actually just showing you what the rule is,
but I'm developing the rule.
So if I have E1 that evaluates to D1 and E2 that evaluates to B2,
what goes here?
It's a good guess.
It's actually D1 plus D2.
So think about this.
E1 evaluates to D1.
So go back to our example which maybe you can see because of the way the screen is but
this is going to evaluate to eight right?
And then it's going to evaluate this one to fifteen.
And so it's going to say the result is eight plus fifteen.
So that's why it's V1 plus V2 here.
That's what it's doing.
It's just breaking this down into a formal language from mathematical language
to describe what we already know how to do instinctively as programmers.
like we're used to looking at code and reasoning about what it does and this is
just providing a formal language around it that's why I said your eyes are gonna
pop out it's really not that hard because it's just understanding how to
look at the symbols and remember what they mean my first time through it had
been 20 years so I had to ask for help so don't freak out
so what just happened there was the whole ad thing moved to the left and so
what we have here is this is parentheses so right so always start
looking here so I have a parentheses around an expression that's what this is
well the premise is that I was about to say something that I'm not sure it's
true so I won't say that but if I have an expression that evaluates to value b
If I put parentheses around that expression by itself, I still just get value b.
We know that, we're used to that, that's all this is saying.
So, if I had the parentheses, that's the parentheses rule.
Again, our xi, this should actually be a xi0.
That's a mistake.
That should be xi0 becomes xi1.
It's just, again, in the process of evaluating this expression,
we might change what variables we have defined with values.
might assign values to new variables.
So this should be xi zero to xi one, and then this would be xi zero to xi one.
Sorry, just change it.
Think about what your program has to do, like what as your program executes,
if you, if, if they're executing a line of code that defines a new variable.
It has to store that somewhere.
That's what the xi stuff is.
Okay, so here's a reduction example.
for an arithmetic expression.
So these are the rules we're going to use.
We just sort of develop those rules.
There's a lot of junk on here, right?
And it's like, oh, mathematical.
What are we doing here?
Well, we want to reduce 2 plus 3 to its semantic value.
So we're going to construct this deduction tree.
What does that mean?
Well, we start with, this is what we're trying to do.
We're trying to reduce 2 plus 3 to its semantic value.
So that's why we got these question marks.
We have a variable store called psi, and then 2 plus 3.
Well in order to evaluate 2 plus 3,
we need to know something about 2 and we need to know something about 3.
And again, we said, very basically, 2 evaluates to itself.
Because it's just so what we're going to get here is the number rule.
So using the num rule, we have to evaluating to itself, by the way,
when you evaluate a literal, an imager literal to itself,
you're not changing the variable store.
So this time you have zi and zi.
Wait, so what's with the horizontal lines?
Right, so you start in the lower part, start with the below the line.
And what the horizontal line is saying is these are the premises that have to be true up here,
and then this is the conclusion down here.
So if this is true and this is true, then this is true.
To use, like, logic.
Does that help?
Yeah.
Don't worry.
There's a couple examples on the study guide that will help you with this stuff.
And we'll definitely go through those next week, by the way.
And then, so, like, what does the downward arrow mean again?
Right.
So that just means that if I think we can go back
to the previous slide where that's defined.
I look at it, and then I forget how to talk about it.
The downward arrow means yield.
It yields.
So if you execute this thing over here,
you're yielding what's over here.
And also, this is your program state.
So you might be changing the variable definitions and values.
Okay.
Good questions.
So we were doing this.
So we had two plus three, so we have to know that two evaluates to two.
It's literal.
And we have to know that three evaluates to three.
So three yields itself, I guess.
And since we know that, we can now start to fill in what's on the right side.
So 2 plus 3 yields 5 because 2 plus 3 is 5.
And the xi hasn't changed because simple addition doesn't involve changing variables you have defined in your program.
So now let's define the rule for multiplication.
So we're gonna reduce 2 plus 3 times 4 to its semantic value, so
we're gonna start there, so we have this expression here,
this is where we're starting.
2 plus 3 times 4, we gotta figure out what goes here,
we gotta figure out what goes above.
What did we need to know, what had to be true,
is the way to ask yourself this question.
So, 2 plus 3, we have to have a rule for this part, and
So we have to have, see, this expression has two parts, it has this two plus three, then it has a times four, right?
So we have to know about two plus three, and we have to know about four.
This is like breaking it down into minutiae, which I have found very tedious in my life as a student.
So you get used to it.
So this part here, the two plus three becoming five, this is everything we did on the previous slide.
So this part here, you can look back at that and see how we got there.
Now the 4, this should be pretty simple.
The 4 evaluates to what?
Itself, 4.
And it's not going to change the psi either.
And now, what goes in on the right down there is 20, right?
Because if we take, this is the part you know.
2 plus 3 times 4 is 5 times 4 is 20, right?
So this is the part where the program is actually executing, and you can do that like in your head because you're looking at it, and it makes sense.
So all this is really saying is, if this is my program and this is, you can reason about what the result is, what did I need to know about the parts of the program to get to that result?
It's breaking the logic down.
logic down. Okay, so now we're going to implement a grammar to represent an
abstract syntax tree as an algebraic data type. So we've done algebraic data
types before. So we're going to have an enumeration called, we're going to call it
expression, and these are going to be the options we have. We have a
a number. We have a plus, where we take the left and the right, which are each expressions,
and we add them together. We have a minus, where we take the left, and then we subtract the right.
And then we have a times, where we take the left and multiply by the right. So these are two
expressions here. We're also going to have in our language, identifiers. So if we have an identifier,
this is like setting x equal, or a equal, or b equal. In our case, we're going to have a single
character identifier for our little language that we're defining here and then we're gonna
also allow for parenthesized expressions so putting in parentheses around so what this is
is a way to model the constructs of the language in Scala and we often refer to this as a domain
specific language because we have a specific domain, it's arithmetic
expressions which are limited right now to literal numbers addition, subtraction,
multiplication. We're also going to allow for, as I said, defining variables and
then we're gonna allow for parentheses in our whole language. So if I want to
I would evaluate, or if I want to represent, sorry,
represent an integer expression as an abstract syntax tree.
So if I have two plus three times x, I could represent that by saying,
I have, on the outside we have two plus this thing, right?
So we have a plus on the outside.
And we have the number two, and then we have this times in here,
so now we're kind of unwrapping this thing.
We have the number three times x.
So x came from nowhere.
You're all like, what's x?
We don't know yet.
This is just an expression that we have to evaluate.
So now we're going to implement the interpreter for
this language, following our formal semantics.
So remember when you saw that xi, and it was like, why is it with this random
brief letter showing up?
Well, it's nothing more than a map.
And in this map, we have, as our keys,
we have single characters.
That's because those come from the identifiers.
You'll see how that works out.
And then our values are all gonna be impagers.
So we'll now define the interpreter signature,
which is gonna follow from, this is some fancy language,
shape of the judgements, right?
So this is a judgment and you have the arrow.
This yields that whole thing is referred to as a judgment.
So I'm evaluating an expression.
So I'm given an expression and a variable store.
And I'm going to get back some integer result
and some new variable store.
So you can click here to get back to the slide.
I think it's this one, yeah, this set of slides
that will take you back to.
as I can it's popping up in my screen there, back to slide four.
These are the reduction rules for integer expression.
So again, we have our numerical rules, we have our addition, etc.
We did that before and we have our parentheses.
We did that before.
So if we apply these over here, what happens?
So if we're implementing this, we look at this.
So if I have an expression and I have a, so if I,
I can just use pattern matching here.
So if I say if I have a number, then the result is just the number and
I didn't change the data store, the variable store.
So I'm just returning back the s that I got.
If on the other hand,
I'm evaluating an expression that happens to be a plus, and
it will be made up of an expression on the left and an expression on the right.
And it will then recursively call evaluate on the first expression.
It will pass the variable store I got, and it will get back a new variable store,
which we'll call S1 here.
Then I'll pass S1 and the second expression into evaluate again,
and give back a new value and S2, a new variable store.
So remember how I kept saying, I may, as I evaluate an expression,
change the variables?
That's what this is doing.
And now it's a result, I'll take the two results, the value one,
value two, add them together and return back that final variable store,
I'm sorry, I'm calling it a data store because I say that at work.
Variable store.
Okay, so that's plus.
Now if I have parentheses, well,
with parentheses you just take the parentheses off.
Like you evaluate the inside, but then you just throw,
you evaluate the inside to a value and then you no longer need the parentheses anymore.
So that's what this is doing here.
I'm just taking that expression I got here, passing it recursively into eval with the variable store,
and whatever it returns, I just return.
There's no addition to do.
So here I did the addition because that was my implementation for addition.
So now let's look at how do we store or look up the values of variables.
So again, we have our syntax defined over there.
We've seen that before on a previous slide.
Looks like our identifiers are limited to single characters lowercase A through Z.
That's what this is saying here.
Our pro, oh, we're going to define program sequence.
So a program sequence could be a program or expression.
Think whenever you see program, think expression.
or an expression, the semi colon followed by another expression.
So this is that sequential stuff we talked about.
Remember in c, it uses like a comma.
Maybe it uses a, I can't remember what it uses.
You don't have to, I don't think you have to memorize that.
But it's gonna do this one, and then it's gonna do this one, right?
It's gonna evaluate this, then it's gonna evaluate that.
And notice this is recursive, so it's either a single,
program, which is gonna be defined lower down, or it's going to be a single
program followed by other ones, multiple ones, potentially multiple. Well, actually
in this case it is definitely, it'll either be single program or it'll have
more programs, more expressions to evaluate. And our program itself will be
identifier colon equal some expression. So here's an example. So you have A equals
two plus three. B equals A and inside here we can do this A equals A plus one
times four. So all this is saying is I can, I can do this addition, store it in
A, update A actually, and then the result of this is going to be whatever A is.
different variables. Let's look at in C and then multiply it by four. Here is a
B. These are examples. So how does this work? So if we're gonna look up a
variable in a variables story, that's what this var rule is going to be. So what we
have is X, this is an identifier. What that's going to mean, the value for X is
It's going to be xi of x.
So this is like calling get on a map.
Calling get and the identifier is x,
so you're saying giving the value that's stored for x.
And just doing the lookup, by the way,
doesn't change the variable stored,
that's why there's no subscripts here.
If we do an assignment, we're going to evaluate an expression
and then we're going to update the state.
So what is this rule going to look like?
So in order for us to have a rule in the first place,
we have to be able to take this e expression and evaluate it.
And we've seen this kind of thing before.
If we have an expression e, we're
going to evaluate it and get a value.
We may be, in the process, updating the variable store.
So if we do that, what happens on the right?
Well we're going to say that doing this assignment is going to yield this value v.
This is like we have in C when you do an assignment.
This is why in C by the way, if you do, just to make it clear,
if you say int x equals y equals 0, you're actually first doing this,
And that evaluates to zero in C, which is why x will also get zero.
So this is the same idea as that, in case you're familiar with that, and that helps.
Okay.
So, the notation we use is this thing here.
So, given this truth here that expression e evaluates to value e, and it may change the variables to learn.
Then if I have this assignment, this is the rule for assignment, my final result of this
expression will be value.
But the interesting thing is that xi changed and we call it xi1 just like we did before
and then we add a little illustration of what changed.
So that's all this is saying.
By doing this assignment, I've now said that x contains the value of v. So not only does
x contain the value of v, but the whole expression evaluates to v.
That's that thing in C.
So I have a sequence of expressions.
So here you can see I have E1 and E2 separated by the semicolon.
Well, what has to be true?
I have to be able to evaluate expression E1,
and I have to be able to evaluate expression E2.
So that's why these pop up here.
We have these two premises.
So what do we think's gonna go here?
Any guess?
Are we still awake?
V1.
You were right on, you were there.
You were there.
So V1 and then E2 is gonna get V2,
and it's going fast but maybe, I don't know.
I will explain it all.
So V1 evaluates to V1,
And in the process, it may change the variable store.
That happens first, then E2 is evaluated second.
And the result will be this V2 value.
And then, so what will the result of this be?
We're used to this, we've seen this in Scala, remember how I said the last
expression in a method definition, for example, is the value of the whole expression.
And that's because of the sequential idea.
So the result here should be, take a guess.
What do we think?
What are the options?
So, if I have a block of code in Scala,
I'm going to use the braces because it's just, it works.
So if I say val y equals seven, the string, and then throw it away immediately, and then
return 42, this is, oh.
I don't need the semicolon because it's Scala.
It would work, but I don't need it.
This is an expression.
This is E1.
We throw it away.
The value of the whole expression here is 42,
even though it's going to do this little side effect.
So it'll do this.
It may change the variable score.
That's what E1 is doing here.
But the ultimate value here is going to end up just being V2.
It doesn't mean that this doesn't happen.
and it will do the work to do the evaluation.
So this is stuff we've already seen and we know about,
but now we're just putting it in this formal mathematical language,
that's all we do.
So what happened again?
We have e1, which evaluated to v1,
we may have changed the variable store,
and then e2 evaluates to v2,
and we inherited the previous variable store because we might have changed something,
and now we're going to change it potentially to zy2.
And so we end up with v2 as our final value for this whole thing,
and we're left with whatever variable store came out of that calculation.
That's what that is.
Okay.
Now we're adding, in this slide, this is very similar to what we had before, right?
So we had number plus minus identify.
identifier and parentheses we're adding times and let's bring some similar we're
adding assignment and we're adding sequence sequential composition which
we just talked through so we can extend our algebraic data type with assignment
and sequential composition also it added times without really saying in the
blow-point credit to that.
So here's our evaluation for these.
So it has the three, the ellipses here,
which is just saying we already saw that on a previous slide.
So if we get, if we're pattern-matching through here,
we get this identity.
So we're still in this key match, right?
So these are the other cases that we can't see.
If we have an identifier of C, well, this is just saying,
look it up in the store.
This is Scala syntax for if I have a store, which remember is a map.
I can use this syntax, it's actually cause apply, and
it actually pulls the value out of the map.
So that's gonna be the result, and it doesn't change the store, and so do.
If I am assigning, whatever I evaluate e to,
the results of that evaluation into the variable x,
I'm going to first have to evaluate e passing the variable store.
I'm going to get back a value, and maybe a changed variables
store.
It might be the same.
We don't know by looking at this part.
And our result of the assignment will
be this value that we assigned to the variable.
And then we call s1.updated, which
is Scala Method on map to update x to contain v.
So x is our character that we use to identify.
And then the sequence, so we have a sequence of two expressions.
We have to evaluate E1, pass the variable store, we get back potentially modified variable store,
then we call evaluate again for the second expression passing the modified variable store,
potentially modified variable store.
We get back a new value of E2, and then we have the new variable store.
and then the result is going to be whatever the value of the second expression was,
whatever it evaluated to, and whatever is stored in the variable store.
That's how we process this sequence of expressions.
When you're doing the S parentheses C,
is that like getting the value stored?
This is like in Java,
it would be like on a hash map you're calling get.
like conceptually, right? Does that make sense?
Yeah.
In Scala, this is just the syntax for that.
It's defined as an apply method,
but it does what you would think a get would do in Java Azure.
Okay.
So, here's our summary.
So we saw a lot of mathematical symbols and it can be overwhelming.
But we know intuitively what we're doing because we're used to thinking about how programs execute and what their behavior is.
We're used to dealing with variables.
We're used to dealing with addition, multiplication, evaluating things, calling functions, sequencing expressions.
We're used to that.
Now we've just given you a formal mathematical language to describe it.
Okay, so operational semantics define a language in terms of operations of an abstract machine.
There are different kinds of semantic definitions, denotational semantics, axiomatic semantics.
I am not up on all of these details.
This is getting into the theory, this is getting into programming language research that I dreamed of doing and
never did because I had a job and a mortgage and decided that I was just kind of keep doing that.
to school all the time for the rest of it.
So then we have judgments and reduction rules.
So they describe the steps of the abstract machine.
And they're expressed as conclusions from premises.
And a deduction tree makes conclusions about the program
from the meaning of the program's components.
So as we were looking at those things,
we were breaking up everything and thinking
about what we needed to know in order
to make the program execute.
Here's some more formal semantics, so conditionals and loops.
So this gets even more.
So if you thought that was overwhelming,
this gets even more fun and interesting.
So this is what an expression now has plus minus times.
As an identifier, it has an expression.
So this is a conditional.
Some expression, the value of that expression
is greater than or equal to the value of this expression, okay?
Again, we have our sequence of programs, which is defined out here.
You have an expression in parens.
These are our identifiers, we saw that before.
Here we have the program sequence.
We have the program itself, which we've seen before.
Now, here's our, our new stuff.
If expression, then expression, else expression, and
And they're using fi in our little language,
just denote the end of an if-then-else.
Or a while expression do and then some other expression,
and then it would terminate with this od.
So the semantics for these, the formal semantics.
Here's the conditional in the case of true.
So we've been talking about this before.
This is non-strict, right?
So we're used to, again, we always start here,
start at the bottom.
If e1 then e2 else e3, and we have our xi here hanging out.
Well, what do we need to know?
We need to know what e1 evaluates to.
So, then we have that premise over here.
e1 evaluates to v1, and then change the variable to store.
This is asserting, this part of the middle is asserting.
v1 is not 0.
So this is using 0 for false, 1 for true.
So v1 is true, it's not 0.
I guess it's using anything that's not 0 as true.
like C would interpret that that way. So, okay, so what we're saying here is in this
case, this is the true rule, so E1 has to evaluate to something that's not false.
And in that case, then we need to know about E2. Notably, we don't need to know
about E3, we don't need to evaluate E3 because that E3 part is non-strict, in
this case. It doesn't evaluate, the whole expression is non-strict, but it doesn't
evaluate e3 unless it has to.
So in this case, because this is going to evaluate to true,
we need to have e2 evaluating to evaluate.
And again, variable sort of changes potentially.
So that's the if true.
And then this is the if false.
So this is just the, I guess you could say, the dual of it.
So you have e1.
This is going to evaluate to zero.
So if that's true, then we need to know about e3.
So this is the same rule, except it's got e2 and e3,
I'm sorry, e2 here for true and e3 here for false.
Same idea.
Now if we have a loop, there are two ways
to think about a loop.
Either our loop is ending, so we start with the loop ending.
Imagine if you have a loop that just never goes into the body,
right?
So while e1, do e2, and then you get your variable stored.
So we're saying that, and we're
using the c sort of way of doing things.
E1 evaluates to v1 and v1 is 0.
So this means that our condition in our while loop evaluates to false.
And in that case, we don't do E, we don't execute this part, so we don't evaluate E2.
So we don't need to know anything about E2, so it's not there in the premises.
So while E1 do E2, we end up with the whole thing.
you're evaluating this expression to be the condition, and that's going to be false here.
And we may have, in the process, changed the variable score.
That's the loop ending.
Then the other case is the loop is recursing.
So you can think of this as the loop is continuing to execute the body of the loop.
So here's my expression.
I have while e1, do e2.
So same as before, but this time,
E1 evaluates to something that is non-zero or not false.
So it is true.
The condition evaluates to true.
So then we have to go into the body of the loop and execute it.
Right?
And so when we execute that, we evaluate E2.
And what this is saying is E2 is going to be sequenced with this.
It's going to actually jump back in, if you think about it,
low-level machine language, it's going to jump back to that place in memory.
but it has to, in not memory, in the program, sorry, in the instructions of the program.
So what it has to do is it actually has to repeat, right?
So if you think about it, all it's doing is when you have a while loop,
you evaluate the condition, and if it's true, you execute the body, and then you loop around.
So in order to loop around, you have to do this sequential thing here.
So that's what it's doing for the while recursive loop.
So this is going to evaluate to true, so we have to evaluate E2,
but then we're going to sequence it with continuing.
So we'll do it again.
And so we'll just apply this rule.
E2 will evaluate to V2.
And so the result here, this is just one iteration of the loop, is V2.
So we can extend our algebraic data type with comparison, conditional, and loop.
So what I've done here is just added the comparisons greater than or equal.
So we have some expression on the left, some expression on the right.
Here's our parentheses again.
Sorry, here's the additionals over here.
So we have if p expression, this is the true expression and
And this is the else expression.
Here's our loop so we have while.
So while P do be.
And so you can write an eval case for that.
So here, here's the absolute value of some expression.
So this is a program that this is actual like in our little language that we
defined like way back on the first slide, this is how you can compute the absolute
value. So it's just if i is positive or greater than or equal to 0, then we just
keep i at i. If not, we just subtract from 0.
And if you think about it, if i is less than 0, like minus 1, this is 0, minus, minus 1,
which gives you plus 1, which gives you the absolute value of minus 1.
This is the expression here of the program.
So we just translated this into this representation here.
So, oh, here's our evaluation.
So now we have our greater than or equal to our if and our while.
Oh, this is a funny little thing.
So this is binding w to this whole expression.
So what this does is it's just some scholar syntax for saying, all right,
I'm matching this case, so the thing I have is a while, and
I want to refer to it typed as a while.
So remember, we have the expr is the super type, right?
So this is saying, well, I'm going to be able to refer to that.
whatever I'm matching, E, as a w of this type now.
Because when I match, I asserted that this was the actual type of this thing
to make this case evaluate to true.
Okay, so what happened?
So let's look at the while first.
So I evaluate e1 passing the variable store.
I get back s1 and my value is v1.
If v1 equals zero, then the whole result of the whole expression is zero, false,
and whatever's left is s1.
Otherwise, I'm going to evaluate this sequence here.
So this is just translating that rule into this code, okay?
And then we added the greater than or equal to.
So this time it's strict, right?
So it has to evaluate e1 and e2 both, so it does that.
E1, get a value V1, new variable store, pass it in.
Passing E2 as well, get back the new variable store in V2.
And then we do this math dot max thing
to determine whether it's greater or equal to.
And this is just a way to get the low level computer
to do that.
That seems like it's the same as before.
So this is our example if we're going to actually
go through the rules.
So we have E1 plus E2.
It's going to give us v1 minus v2.
this slide is broken.
This slide looks broken.
Something isn't right.
Let me check.
It's also 847, so maybe I have a bug in this slide.
I wonder why that says v1 minus v2.
V2.
This is the absolute value example.
So it feels like something is wrong.
So if we have the sub rule, I think that should be a minus.
I think that's what's wrong here.
I think this is a bug in the slide.
So we evaluate V1 to get V1.
We evaluate V2 to get V2.
And we should be doing subtraction here.
I have to double check that.
I sync these slides with the other professors
so I'll often be like, hey why did you change that,
why is that there?
So we have assignment over there.
So here when we do the assignment,
we have the expression value into value,
this is the premise again,
and when we update the variable store,
we're updating it with x containing value v.
I think this is just showing you the rules.
So yeah, that's definitely wrong, e1 minus e2.
And then over here on the right, we have our sequential composition rule which we saw earlier.
And now we have our comparison rule. This is what our comparison rule looks like.
So it starts to, like, make your head explode, right? So, e1, e2.
Those two expressions have to evaluate to values in order for us to do this comparison.
And we may be changing the interval stores on the way.
And then what this little syntax, this little notation I guess is doing is saying,
I'm going to compute the max of this.
It's too late for me to do math, so I'm not going to double check that.
This is the greater than or equal to rule.
And then here's our conditional rules, which we've done before.
This is where it gets crazy.
So my eyes popped out of my head last night.
You don't have to memorize any, like, this stuff on this slide.
Like, these slides are still here.
And I could go through them.
But I am being lazy because it's late.
And...
You don't have to worry about this.
This is the factorial example.
So there's the code.
This is applying the rules to make that program execute.
And then this is the reduction.
Once I saw the word lemma, I was like,
oh, I feel like I'm in advanced theory classes
and I don't feel like doing lemmas.
So you don't have to either.
And I'm sure of that because last quarter
I told them the same thing.
And the point here is that we're going
to focus on what's in the quiz and what's
in the study guide and stuff.
So don't freak out.
If you get what's in the study guide, you're going to be good.
Definitely do it.
So we're left with 10 minutes,
which isn't really enough time.
We could do maybe one or two questions,
but if you all wanna just call it a night,
you can do that too.
I'll definitely make time next week
to review some of the study guide stuff,
especially the formal cementing stuff.
But please bring questions,
because if you're working on it,
hopefully you're working on it,
I mean, you are gonna have a new homework
and a new quiz,
but if you're working on it and you've got questions,
bring them to class so we can talk for them.
Otherwise, what I'll do is I'll allocate a certain amount of time.
I'll just go through certain questions
and pick the ones that I think are more challenging.
So all right.
So what do I want to do?
Want to go through anything, or you're all like, no, it's 8.51.
Let me go home.
I used to sit in your chairs, by the way.
There's one professor I used to watch on Saturday morning,
because I was like, oh, I can't.
I just can't.
Seems like you should come to next class with some questions.
Come to class with questions next week, yes.
Because I would like to make it as interactive as possible.
If you're struggling through this, you're studying,
I want to be able to use some time to help you
work through that stuff.
You can also come to office hours.
That's what's there.
All right, well then we'll call it a night.
And I will see you next week.
Alright, thanks everybody!
I hope you enjoyed this video.
so
it
you
I'll see you next week.
Yeah, take care.
Me too.
Thank you.
So, let's go.
I think I'm going to put a little on the top of my head.
Okay, good afternoon.
so
do
So, now I'm going to put a little bit of a bottle of water, so I'm going to put a bottle of water.
I'm going to put it in water, and I'm going to put a bottle of water.
I'm going to put a bottle of water.
So I really like to eat the food.
I like to eat the food.
It's good to eat the food.
I'm going to eat the food.
So, let's take another break.
Amen.
Thank you.
...
It's kind of dry.
The only of the ants I would say the hydrogens are
regions.
The
Thank you.
So, let's go.